INVERSETEMPERATURE.NET tim.genewein@gmail.com

[®]Tim Genewein

PHD STUDENT

MAX PLANCK INSTITUTE FOR INTELLIGENT SYSTEMS
MAX PLANCK INSTITUTE FOR BIOLOGICAL CYBERNETICS

Research

Bounded rationality: optimal decision-making under limited information processing resources. I am working on an information theoretic optimality principle for bounded rational inference and decision-making that leads to the formation of natural **hierarchies of abstraction**. Closely related topics are structure learning and model selection of which I have tested theoretical aspects in sensorimotor paradigms in virtual reality experiments. Find more about my research on inversetemperature.net/research.

Key topics

Hierarchies of abstraction[1,4]

Information theoretic optimality principle that leads to the formation of hierarchies of abstraction.

Structure learning [2]

Humans extract statistical invariants to enhance their performance. Behavior can be modelled with a hierarchical Bayesian model.

Model selection [3,5]

Humans select among learned structures in a way that is quantitatively consistent with Bayesian model selection.

Education

PhD: Computational Neuroscience

Max Planck Institute for Intelligent Systems Max Planck Institute for Biological Cybernetics

since 2012

Topic: Stucture learning through hierarchies of abstraction (supervised by: Daniel A. Braun)

MSc, BSc: Telematics

Graz University of Technology, completed with distinction

2006-2012

Focus on: Computational Intelligence and Autonomous Robots.

MSc Thesis: Structure learning for robotic motor control (supervised by: Wolfgang Maass, Gerhard Neuman)

Skills

knowledge	practical	languages
Information theory	Probabilistic inference	Julia
Machine learning	Hieararchical Bayesian modelling	Python
Sensorimotor learning	Neural networks	Matlab
Decision theory	Computer vision	C#
Robotics	Embedded systems	C/C++

Experience

NTE Systems

Software developer (part-time)

11/2009-03/2011

Encapsulation of Zig-Bee communication (SOAP) for a smart home automation controller Web-service implementation on micro-controller platform (SOAP, .NET Micro Framework)

IVM Engineering

Junior consultant, software developer (part-time)

08/2008-10/2009

Encapsulation of CAN-bus communication module (high-level backend in .NET) Applicability of aspect-oriented programming in a commercial software project

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Genewein, Leibfried, Grau-Moya, Braun (2015) Bounded rationality, abstraction and hierarchical decision-making: an information-theoretic optimality principle. Frontiers in Robotics and Al
- [2] Genewein, Hez, Razzaghpanah, Braun (2015) Structure Learning in Bayesian Sensorimotor Integration. PLoS Computational Biology
- [3] Genewein, Braun (2104) Occam's Razor in sensorimotor learning. Proceedings of the Royal Societey B
- [4] Genewein, Braun (2013) Abstraction in Decision-Makers with Limited Information Processing Capabilities, NIPS 2013 workshop on Planning with Information Constraints. arXiv
- [5] Genewein, Braun (2012) A sensorimotor paradigm for Bayesian model selection. Frontiers in Human Neuroscience

For a complete list (including posters and talks) see inversetemperature.net/publications